The treaties of so-called "economic partnership" with african, caribbean and pacific countries
are seen with some reluctance by their governments, whatever their political persuasion.
In truth, these treaties are not partnership agreements.
They are immigration-producing machines
since they have the immediate effect of reducing the revenues of the concerned states
and therefore of reducing health, social, education and facilities-building programmes in these countries.
Above all, because of these treaties, our goods flood local economies and destroy them,
which entails an increase in unemployment and forces rural populations to move towards urban areas.
In these rural areas, peasants are ruined because of the export of our agricultural products.
We observe an increase in single-crop farming that pollute soils
and destroy the cultural practices in these regions.
Finally, these treaties force people into exile from rural to urban areas
and from cities to foreign countries.
I think History will judge our blindness very severely,
as well as our voting for such agreements that
put insuperable pressure on the governments in these areas.